When we talk about open data, we think about
public data...
But there are many other data
which are interesting in our
everyday lives and that companies produce.
There is one particularly interesting domain, it's
food, where it's not about public data
but data of
public interest.
Today, I'll present you
Open Food Facts which is a
new way of opening
data owned by companies.
With the palm oil scandal,
the horsemeat scandal,we saw that
the food industry
is not always transparent
This lack of transparency is
not good for anyone: This is not
good for the consumer who doesn't know what he eats
and has no options to choose from.
This is not good for the environment: look at the palm oil case,
with the deforestation in
Malaysia and Indonesia.
Finally, this is not good for
companies either, since
there it create a lack
of trust towards them.
We said ourselves: if people can create the biggest
encyclopedy in the world,
if they can work together to create a map of the world which is
more detailed than the one Google made,
Why not try to create a database on
food products?
That's how, one year and a half ago, Open Food Facts started.
Open Food Facts is a database,
based on similar principle to Wikipedia
it's collaborative, people with a smartphone
like you and me:
we scan bar codes, we take
pictures of ingredients,
nutrition facts and every bits of information
then we put them all in a database
Today, there are almost 700 contributors
with over 12.000 products
everything is put into
an open database
under Open Database Licence.
A quick word on crowdsourcing:
it's working well
in fact in one year and a half,
we went over 10.000
products in France
It's working because it is
data of public interest
There is a lot of people today which are
careful about
what they eat
because they are alergic or intolerant to gluten
because they are careful about their health or cholesterol
or about palm oil...
What could be the use of a
database with information
on food?
The first and foremost:
is to decrypt the labels
like all these E330, E150d, etc...
These are additives.
There is about 2.000 of them...
and most people know ... none.
What we can easily do,
it's to say E150d
it's the colorant which is in your
can of coke, it's caramel and
the complete name which is not on the label, is sulfite ammonia caramel
in California, is now on the list of
carcinogenic chemical substances
better to avoid it then...
Coca Cola removed the E150d from the US market.
but for us, in Europe, we still have this Coca Cola with
sulfite ammonia caramel
On the Fraise Tagada (Tagada strawberry) example
where there is not at all the word fraise (strawberry)
written on the packaging because
there isn't any in it.
However, there is cochineal, it's E120, it's a
red colorant.
and it's extract - I discovered this doing the project -
which is extracted from cochineal insect, some small insects which are farmed on
cactus in Mexico.
You squeeze your little insects, and then you have some cochineal juice
and it allows you to color your
candies but also the taramasalata
because taramasalata is made of cod eggs which are unfortunately gray...
so if we add a drop of
red colorant inside, some cochineal juice
it become pink, of course, it's much more pleasant
and we indeed realize,
looking in our database,
that we can look for all
of the products that contain
this carminic acid, this cochineal
and there plenty of things we
wouldn't suspect containg some
the saucissons, for them to be more red, we put some juice of
cochineal inside, the orange
cheese crust
it's some yellow colorant with red colorant
Also something I like
and which is interesting on
labels, in UK,
is what we call the traffic light nutrition facts
it's showing you immediately with
red, orange and green labels
be careful, there is too much fat, there is too much
sugar, there is too much salt.
In 2011, there was a lot of ecologists and consumers groups which
have tried to propose this to the European parliament
but there has been a huge lobby from
the food industry
who didn't want
to put a red flag
on a bag of chips.
So it has been rejected in 2011.
However, it's a thing that we can easily display
nicely this is a new app
that I am currently
developing
where we
put our mobile phone in front of
any product
and we can then see information like these
traffic light type of nutrition facts.
When you have a database of
products, it's also tempting, of course,
to compare between products, to compare my ketchup
to the average ketchups, it's written 30% less of sugar.
Is this true?
That the kind of things we can check:
Here, I show you a graphic
where I choose to display every sodas
with sugar on one axis and additives on the other.
you can go on the OpenFoodFacts.org website and within
with a few clicks, you can have the
same graphic with charcuterie and
the fat and the salt for example.
So, all of this
these data, these data on
what we're eating,
I think that this is data
so much important that they must be
public, they must be available,
so that's why we have, we have
we have created this
database.
There is a lot of startup that has been launched on this topic
of food,
and often, they wanted you
to scan the products and
that you send them some photos but after, they keep
the data for themselves, it's like their
war chest, it's what they
try to make business with
while, well, us, we are a non-profit
project
we have nothing to monetize and on the contrary, we
take full benefit of having these data
being useful
and used for as many applications as possible.
I'll show you some examples
of reuse:
this is a website called "C'est fabriqué près de chez vous"
(made near me)
it's done with these little codes which are
on food products that we
call packaging code
it's looks like
EMB 56081 E
so 56081 it's not a postal code but it's French INSEE code of the town
well we can now know that it's
produced in Theix in
Morbihan (Britanny, France).
We can now look somewhere on the French map where are
produced these products.
and then, what's fun, it's to look at all the other
products that are produced by the same
factory
well in our factory
in Theix, Morbihan
there is beans and carots, so on from the Daucy brand, it's the factory
of Daucy, but it's producing also
food for all the other brands
that are distributors.
This is a small pedagogical game
with data that we gather
The game goes like this: we show you a
product
and you try to find
their sugar equivalent in
in number of sugar cubes
and sometimes you can be very stunned of
the quantity of sugar in
some food.
Soda, of course yes, we think
that it's sugary
however, fruit juices we may know a little less that it's
as sugary as the sodas and that
in my liter of banana juice
or pinapple juice, there is 45 sugar cubes
That's all, the presentation is done.
We have a wiki, everything is open,
the source code of the software is on Github